I've been getting after it a whole lot
lately with the iron bull competition
bar and aside from the sheer versatility
it brings to the table my three favorite
things are the affordable price tag the
four different finishes it comes in and
it comes in two different sizes if
you're looking for a new barbell to
serve as the only one in your home gym
but you don't want to spend over 300
bucks I think your search might have
just ended and I think you know what
time it is now at least I hope you do
it's time for a full review let's get to
it
[Music]
what's up everybody it's Jake back in
the barbing garage gym and for today's
video I've got the iron bull competition
bar Ino review if you don't know how
this whole process works I'm going to
talk about a lot of stuff in this video
today but specifically we're going to
talk about some money some pros and cons
I've noticed while working out with this
bar most importantly who should or maybe
should not purchase it for their home
gym now one more quick thing before I
start talking my head off I got to let
y'all know we've reviewed a ton of
barbells on barb. comom and we did the
hard part for you and made a best list
of all of our top choices so if you want
to check that out all you got to do is
search barbend best barbells it's going
to pull right up for you you can find
out for yourself which ones we like the
best
[Music]
okay so let's talk some pros and cons
here and I think the first thing I got
to talk about is the money don't worry
I'm going to expand in just a second and
talk about the different coating options
remember there's four different ones you
can purchase but the cheapest this bar
is it's 200 bucks and that's pretty
cheap compared to plenty of other
multi-purpose bars out there they're
going to be $400 to $500 this is also
you know comes in two different sizes 15
and 20 kg so it's going to allow all
athletes to you know get used us out of
this bar and then also this is a
multi-purpose bar so it's going to save
you money again as opposed to purchasing
you know a powerlifting bar just for
your power lifts and an Olympic Bar just
for your Olympic and Crossfit style
lifts speaking of that versatility so
you have ball bearings in the loading
sleeves right here it's going to create
a pretty solid rate of spin as you're
going to do hang cleans power cleans you
know whatever it is but also the
knurling right here is pretty moderate
it's a volcano style knurling so each
individual marking right here kind of in
like a volcano does so you get four
points of contact with every each and
every single individual point so it
really increases the grip but since it's
moderate you know it's not going to rip
your hands up and it's going to be great
for anybody who is you know doing
explosive movements like that where the
bar is rotating in your hands and one
more one more quick thing I forgot to
mention the reason that you know these
ball bearings are nice in the loading
sleeves is because it reduces the amount
of torque that your wrists and your
elbows endure I guess you could say as
you're going to do any style of lift
like you know power clean again for
example where that bar is rotating and
you're having to use a lot of force you
know on your joints now when it comes to
those cons we got to talk about the
knurling first yeah it is going to be
you know solid for anybody who is doing
you know High repetition movements like
that but at the same time it can be
pretty slick at times so you know if
you're a dedicated
powerlifter you're doing a bunch of
heavy deadlifts you know whatever the
case is that you might not be too crazy
about this you know texture knurling all
that it's all personal preference and so
it's going to vary from person to person
but that's definitely something you need
to be aware of and then lastly it's just
not the best at any one lift just
because it can be used across all of
them doesn't mean it's going to
outperform a power bar for your power
list or an Olympic Bar for your Olympic
list so just keep that in
mind okay so let's expand on the money
now as I promised and let's start with
the 15 Ker bar so it comes in two
different options $200 for the black
chrome and it's going to be$ 250 for the
pink cak Co now 20 KG Bar remember this
is black zinc so zinc is a little bit
more resistant to rust and corrosion so
definitely just keep that in mind this
is also going to cost you 200 bucks
while the red sakote for the 20 kg bar
is also 250 now with the stainless steel
it only comes in you know the 20 kg bar
but it's going to cost you 300 bucks I
didn't stutter I didn't say it wrong
$300 dude that is a crazy deal honestly
you know most stainless steel bars are
going to run you close to $500 and if
you don't already know stainless steel
offers the highest level of protection
against rust and corrosion so you have
to spend you know less time cleaning
your bar which you you should still
clean it they all get gross over time
but you won't have to worry about rust
and corrosion as much and not everybody
you know has a climate control gym they
work out in keep all their gear in so
that's really going to come in handy if
that's you now end of the day you know
obviously that stainless steel is way
below Market average you know barbell is
like the Rogue Ohio bar excuse me Rogue
Ohio bar stainless steel version like I
said it's going to cost you about $500
so that's a big chunk of change you're
saving the rest of them though it's
honestly pretty average compared to the
rest of the market but at the same time
you know you've got barbells you know
like the rep Colorado bar which is a
really nice barbell but the cheapest one
for that is still 320 bucks or so so
you're saving you know over $100
compared to many other barbells out
there and I think that's a really
awesome thing for people who are working
with the tight
budget okay so as far as actual
construction goes the 15 kgr bar is
right around 79 in long with 13-in
loading sleeves and a diameter of 25 mm
while this 20 kg bar is 86.7 in long
with 16.4 in loading sleeves and a 28.5
mm diameter now you do have dual neural
markings right here ipf and iwf standard
international powerlifting and
weightlifting Federation for those who
don't know now as far as actual knurling
goes you could say it's moderate it is
moderate but it probably leans more
towards you know passive now you do
still have you know a volcano style
knurling so it's going to help increase
the friction between your hands and the
bar but you know powerlifters may not be
too crazy about it so just you know kind
of keep that in mind now this is a
multi-purpose bar and that's because you
have eight needle bearings in either
loading sleeves but it also looks like
you have bronze bushings right here so
you're going to have a pretty solid rate
of spin now something worth noting about
the the bearings is that they will
degrade at a faster rate than bronze
bushings will so it's kind of a
trade-off you get more spin but if you
only had you know bronze bushings in
this bar the sleeves would essentially
last you longer now that's not to say
it's only going to last you a year or
two it's definitely going to last you
longer than that but just kind of keep
that in mind now you do have a grooved
pattern on these loading sleeves and
that's going to help you you know keep
your weight plates in their original
placement this really comes in handy you
know as you're doing deadlifts you drop
that bar any anything where you're
dropping the bar with loaded loaded
weight on it right as you do that the
weights tend to you know slide down the
loading sleeves so that Groove pattern
helps but you should definitely still
use some collars you know and just kind
of lock them into place to help you out
you also get a lifetime warranty on this
bar which I think is a pretty sweet
thing now it's not going to cover any
negligent use such as using damaged
weight plates but it's still nice that
you get to have that and then lastly you
know I just touched on it but remember
this bar is available in four different
finishes right so I've got the black
zinc right here in front of me it comes
in two different colored cerakote
options black chrome and that stainless
[Music]
steel okay so I want to show you guys
the anatomy of these loading sleeves and
really just show like you know you this
is a affordable barbell but there's some
really sweet specs here right so let go
ahead and take the rest of this loading
sleeve off so I mentioned you have
needle bearings and you have bushings in
the loading sleeve so I mentioned eight
needle bearings there's actually four of
these in each loading sleeve so if you
can see up close there's these little
rollers in here right so that is what is
spinning as you can see I'm kind of
spinning it right there so there four of
these in each barbell on loading sleeve
excuse me actually I'll show you this
other end right here so this is your
bronze bushing right here it's going to
help with the spin a little bit too so
these produce a really solid rate of
Spin and like I said this is how you
clean and care for your loading sleeves
I have a kind of a goofy video on on how
to properly do that but the information
is there if you want to go check it out
so over time you know these are going to
you know have dust and dirt kind of
built up and what you want to do is take
it apart as I did kind of wipe all this
oil off right now this is really solid
oil still so I'm not going to touch that
right now but you'd wipe it off get a
three in- one multi-purpose oil you know
kind of rub it in and then basically
you're good to go and then you'll just
do this reverse process right here of
putting all your stuff back together I'm
not going to bore you with that right
now but that's basically you know how
that process is going to look actually
you know what let's just keep rolling
because this doesn't take you a whole
lot of time this is a very essential
thing to do for your barbell and it
really like it's it's effortless sorry
must snpp ring pliers are over here so
get yourself a nice set of Snapper ring
pliers like these right here push that
on in snaps right in then you got your
incap right here push that on in and
then you got your
other snap
ring this one does get a little bit
tricky
sometimes doesn't matter how many times
you do it sometimes it just takes a
second and that's all right right it but
like I said this is going to increase
the longevity of your barbell and it's
important to do really not that bad once
you get the hang of it and that's what
is you know creating that solid rate of
spin now let me step back into the rack
here now let's talk about the knurling
you know once again it is kind of
passive that could be good for some
people could be kind of bad for others
you know it really just depends on what
style of lift you're doing so once again
this isn't multi-purpose bar it can
handle all of it but you know the
nerling here is probably you know best
suited for Olympic and Crossfit style
lifts however you do have you know dual
neural markings right here this inside
one is ipf other one is iwf powerlifting
Federation weightlifting Federation so
it's going to allow you to you know get
that identical hand placement as you go
to get set for your lifts remember this
version right here has
190k tensil strength rating 190,000
tensil strength rating the stainless
steel is 200,000 tinel strength so you
know the 10,000s were not that big of a
difference but whichever one you go for
it's really solid it's going to be able
to handle all that punishment you know
that you bring its way you also do not
have any center earling right here I
like that you know with a power bar it's
nice having it you know whenever you're
going to do your back squats and in
general you can make the argument that
it's it's worth having it I prefer to
not have that right here especially you
know with a multi-purpose bar whenever
you're going to do any lift or that bar
is resting on your chest you know it's
not going to you know tear you up right
here
so I think this barbell is an ideal
solution for anybody who's working with
a tight budget remember it's as cheap as
200 bucks and only as expensive as $300
it's also going to be an awesome option
for anybody looking for a bar that can
be used across all of their lifts since
it is in fact a multipurpose bar and
then if you're in the market for a 15
kgr bar I think this is a really solid
option to consider as well now on the
flip side for somebody who has rough
hands you might not be too crazy about
this nerling right here it's a little
bit on the the passive side of things
and that could come you know into a
negative effect I guess you could say as
you're going to do those power lifts you
know especially a deadlift and that just
you know could start to get pretty
slippery on you as you start to lift
some heavy weight and then another thing
here is that you know yes it is a
multi-purpose bar yes it can be used
across all of your lifts but it's
remember like I said earlier it's not
the best at any one you know particular
lift so if you are a dedicated lifter
and you know one end of the spectrum I
think you should go after a SP
[Applause]
bar all right well that's all she wrote
on today's review over the iron bull
competition bar I think this is a really
solid option for beginners to consider
but also for anybody who's on a tight
budget since it can be used across all
of your lifts that being said I don't
think it's the best option for anybody
who has a heavy emphasis in powerlifting
since the nerling is a little bit
passive thanks for watching y'all I hope
this video was really helpful and I was
able to break down everything there is
to to know about this barbell as always
stay posted for my next video but for
now head over to Barb ben.com cuz we
have a full written article about this
barbell all you need to do is search
barbend ironbull competition Bar review
it's going to pull right up for you you
can go over every single thing we talked
about here today I'll catch youall next
[Music]
time
n